All right, welcome back to cohort
8. We are definitely in the
backstretch in the final
chapter. So, we'll have two discussions
on chapter
5. Then these last uh weeks, we tend to
not record them. It's usually just like
looking at
the feedback form, giving giving people
an opportunity to fill out the feedback
form. I I'll update the numbers. Um, and
then just looking at a lot of the
thoughts people have had
uh about future textbook groups and just
as we get further and further from the
initial book and sort of explore other
reading groups. So, they're just fun and
then that kind of closes this phase.
then we'll probably resume with chapter
six before uh in in some months but
first let's go to oh and one other uh
piece I just wanted to show initially
Sanjie Nam Jooshi who's the author of
the the soontobe published the
fundamentals
uh two textbooks with with one of them
coming out um he has also made an open
source
repo that I'm just running it right now
locally. And this is what it pops up
from a Docker
container. So that's kind of like uh
veering from the textbook group, but all
the different references and things that
people bring up and and um just a and
and it's also a cool place to explore
like literature meta
analysis and uh other kinds of
literature based methods.
Okay, chapter five
though. Would anyone like
to start with any any any recap of
five or question or section from five
uh I found it uh I'm sculowskas I found
it very helpful um just in terms of
making sense of active inference in
terms of uh domain and maybe this is the
domain where it uh was first uh
recognized and formulated u and so uh uh
which is neur neuroscience brain
sciences and
so for me personally personally like I
like they make a note about the relating
of the discrete models with the
continuous models how that functions uh
and so uh I think that there's something
more to be discovered there and um I
guess there's this theme of message
passing so that's a code word I think
for neurotransmitters saying that um uh
you can model uh neurotransmission
um with um Markoff processes and thus
active inference becomes relevant and
then there's also uh examples
um with um the cortical columns in the
cortex you know trying to make
layers and how are those
layers and so uh or uh I'm also
interested like in the subcortical
structures like the basil ganglia you
have a excitatory uh I think direct
pathway and inhibitory indirect pathway
that are connecting with motor uh
capabilities um
sensory very helpful this idea that you
need to with
precision of the understanding I guess
of the let's say sensors the proprio
proprio centers I think um sensors like
they need if if they think that they're
not moving, they're not ever going to
move. So you have to make them doubt
whether they're static and then then you
can let them think, oh, you're moving
and then they start to move. Uh so
that's a very interesting um dynamic. I
think that that really helps to
um I I think it it's just it helps to
think about what's going on and then
that makes active inference uh
intuitively an attractive framework and
then mathematically interesting. How how
you know helpful.
Thank you. Great comments.
Anyone else have like a section or or a
comment on
five. I'll just say more like that. It
really opens up a lot of things to think
about. And I think also it makes clear
that active inference has you know has
something this very important idea that
you
know lost you for a few seconds and
okay
yeah two flavors of the same thing and
so that there's three energy principle
um can be understood in either you know
can can get either one of those going.
Um but um it also shows like that
there's a lot there. It's just a it's
just a tool for thinking about these
things. But as far as actual
implementation interpretation, there's a
lot that it doesn't really um do for
itself. You have to kind of like come up
with a picture or a model or idea. And
so one of the things that fascinated me
was just appreciating oh that there's
this whole language of
neurotransmitters. Uh there's this whole
um alphabet let's say of of
possibilities. And uh I don't think
active inference directly speaks to what
they mean. It just kind of explains some
of the framework for that language. So
that's that's what I inferred.
Thanks. Great comments. Yeah.
Wow. There's a lot it doesn't do for
itself. That's kind of a function of the
the the
generality. Um, and then like the table
of
neurotransmitters and these specific
systems. This is where the sort of
specific experimenting, hypothesis,
testing, falsification, it's like we're
not seeing any evidence from lesion
studies or from this C elegance model
and this mouse model. We're not seeing
evidence for this cognitive function in
connection to that one. So that's kind
of a
neuroarchchitecture agnostic way to
frame it. Like we tried to apply this
Baze model to these different and we
found that there were these diff um
these different structural models of
parameters in play. And then it it could
also connect with a more explicitly
mechanistic research agenda like arising
from SPM and the empirical work on fMRI
and neuroiming where they take similar
models to these and and look at how
these parameters differ keeping the edge
constant or look at how certain
parameters differ um under different
structural hypothe hypothesis like in
attention or or um unattended context.
That's kind of the
SPM, fMRI, EEG classic studies which are
kind of explored in chapter 9. So it's
like chapter 5 is the first time that
we're encountering the specific
um
cognitive in a continuum to
neuromchanistic
hypothesis falsifiable
um drawn from larger possible
hypotheses. Like if the even just
keeping the same variables in play,
there are other structural hypotheses
that we could imagine. Um and and there
might be a given area of phase space,
could be small area, could be a huge
area where like two structurally similar
models are can't be one can't be said to
be like better than the other like
they're not identifiable from each
other. And that that comes up with like
structural equation
modeling in just any kind of statistical
method.
[Music]
Um, anyone else want to go to a a
part where we could try to look at one
of the papers that are cited for more
information or look at one of the
uh three subsystems more. Yeah, Sylvia,
um, I do have a part that I've been
thinking about, haven't really gotten my
head around. is on page
95. So section 5.5
um at the bottom bit of that page it
says the relationship between the two is
simple. If we have very precise beliefs
about how data are generated from hidden
states then our beliefs about hidden
states can be updated by observing data
more than if we are not confident in
those beliefs. I'm just wondering why
isn't this the other way around?
as in if you are less confident that you
might have to update
more that that same exact question. I'm
glad you asked
it. Yeah, it is a good question. So,
um two two cases
Um, one of them is the prior looks like
a very broad
Gaussian like it's um 10 plus or minus
5 and then a new observation comes in.
So, so it's not a very precise belief.
New observation comes in and kind of
shifts the whole Gaussian
slightly. That that's a low precision
belief updating slightly.
If there's a high precision
belief, then it's like a a 10 plus or
minus one. And if that same measurement
of um 14 comes
in, the the posterior could
move a a lot to
that. Now whether the wide
uh high variance or the low variance
prior moves not at all or all the way is
like an attention precision
question. So I think here um it just
looking at all other things being equal
basian and
updating I think that
um for the same
attention
the tight distribution would update
possibly
less because the the the observation is
just so
unlikely. So it's like the the posterior
might not update that much but maybe
because here they're focusing just on
the precision
but but it is separable from from see
seemingly from like what you what the
actual variance of the target
distribution is whereas if you if you
believe if you believe that it's an
informative
channel you update more
and can I give an example and Do you see
if it's Yeah. So, let's say I'm
wondering where my brother is. So, one
very vague idea, my brother went out. A
less vague would be my brother went out
to the store. And more precise would be
my brother went out to 7-Eleven. So, you
see, if he went out to 7-Eleven, it's
easy to for that to turn out to be
needing to be updated. You know, lots of
things could say, well, he's he's on the
other side of town, right? Like, so, but
he's on the other side of town. He may
still have gone to a store, right? So
the more precise it is, the more easy it
is vulnerable to, you know, being
affected by more information. That's the
way I'm
I I think that's it's related. I I hope
I'm not
like o over splitting it, but it's like
let's just go with a 7-Eleven case. So
there's like the there's three people in
the room you could ask um and they're
going to tell you at those three levels
of course graining of location like the
10's place, the one's place or the
decimal place or all three. But then
attention would be on a zero to 100 or 0
to one. How much are you going to update
to that
belief including not not mattering at
all? Like if you already believed that
he went out, then zero or 100 attention
to the person who's going to tell you
just that isn't going to update your
belief at all, whether you're paying
attention to that first person or not,
because it's like the ball is already at
the bottom of the bowl. It's it's
already at the maximum likelihood
solution. Whereas, um, if you had it
100% belief, you're going to update to
just whatever the person tells you.
So that's the P. So it's like the the
the or just like the the propriception
coming from a hand like that little
corpsical or or unit could be firing
madly or not at all or anywhere in
between. Now that could have any
relationship to whether there's like
actually heat or something. But so
that's whether the three people in the
room are telling the right information.
But then there's the attention to
that. So if there's
precision, if we have precision on the A
matrix, which still could be ambiguous
or
not, then beliefs about hidden state can
be updated by observing data more.
So it's kind of like scaling the the
import the the impact on the basian
updating of the beliefs about hidden
states from attention to the
observation.
Um can you elaborate on the row of
attention in relation to precision again
please?
Yeah, I think um attention and precision
and temperature sometimes are used in
sort of
um
similarish ways. Um, but even like the
attention in the
transformer, like this is kind this is
kind of a uh superb built out
version, but in its most
[Music]
um single
parameter
setting, it's just like how much
impact on on the latent
state is is being influenced influenced
by the new observation coming in. So
like complete attention is updating all
the way to the new data
point. Like someone says it's four and
go it's four and then it's five. Okay,
it's five. So it's now that could have
whatever variance that's whether the
object level distribution is just has a
given var small or a large variance or
whatever or it's a or it's a um dro
delta function so it's just single
parameter like there's no variance
um and then no attention which is kind
of one of the one of
the multiple places with attention
confidence
belief where it's like a psychological
term moved into stats. Now coming back
to confusingly either apply or not apply
to that psychological phenomena or be
some other
psychological phenomena. But it's like
if something's not paying attention at
all, the other extreme, it doesn't have
an impact on it
learning. It just it was it was
functionally didn't
happen. So that's like if you have a
um you have some a matrix
um the ambiguity matrix mapping
observations to latent states. So it
could be like a uniform distribution
which just is is like the symbols coming
over the channel don't reduce
uncertainty about the hidden states or
it could be like an identity matrix with
just the symbols coming over the channel
have complete concordance to this latent
space um or or other matrices in
between. So that's about like the kind
of object level properties of the
mapping between the observations and the
hidden state in the values of the A
matrix. Um
then that could just have sort of a a
implicit kind of attention of one.
If if you wanted to explore different
impacts of that
mapping on belief updating or of
modulation within a model of how even um
uh those
beliefs impact
updating. Um having another kind of like
a volume knob
parameter that can go between
this channel is not having any impact to
this channel has a high
impact is kind of a common
mechanism. So sometimes it's done with
like a 0ero to one just type
scaling, sometimes it's done with like
more of a just other ways. And then even
though it's a little bit different,
here's where there's like a temperature
[Music]
um just scaling different
variables because that's kind of one of
the ways when it gets down to the
calculation of it. That's that's like
how these matrices can come to have
different impact on each other is just
through scaling them like by a
coefficient or raising or lowering them
to a coefficient.
Thank you.
Multiplicative weight is a coefficient.
Yeah. I guess in terms of math it it can
be understood more
intuitively. Um so is it is it fair to
kind of understand this
as I don't know the the update will be
reducing
uncertainty
and in our beliefs about hidden state
can be updated by observing data more in
that it's kind of like you become more
certain about something. Hence you you
become more confident in that
belief and that's why it's more than if
we are no confidence in those
beliefs. I think it's the belief in that
stream of data is is does that help
because I think that's what I was
getting kind of tripped up because I
just kept thinking okay there's a
generative model that is modeling you
know whatever that hidden state is and
so I'm pretty sure I know what that
thing is and then so why do I need all
the precision of that channel but it's
almost like I am more I think this is
really about a a belief or a
prediction maybe a model of whatever
that is coming from that observable data
as opposed to whatever that thing is.
And I don't know if that makes sense. So
it's so it's like confidence
in whatever I'm going to get next. It's
almost like the this if there is a model
here, it's like it's a model of whatever
is passing that message up. And I could
be wrong about that, but I don't know if
that helps or if it's accurate.
Yeah. just one one to Sylvia then than
then Andrew. So here with the
multiplicative updating on prediction
errors. So it's like let's just say that
that we're we're
we're two two entities are in a zero to
100 action belief space which could be a
belief about action like how likely they
are to do something. So that's a huge
benefit of having direct beliefs about
action as opposed to like a reward
function is talking about latent states
could be talking about a sensemaking
latent state could be talking about an
action inference. So that's one benefit
that's that's not really mentioned here.
So now the observation comes in like
it's it's a temp it's it's a temperature
0 to 100 and then there's a 0 to 100
action space for a heater. And so one
entity might have a um uh the the
thermometer reading comes in five units
over their belief. So just at the pure
error calculation, they're five points
off. But then one agent's attention to
those five kind of raw units of of like
that those are the units that are kind
of getting pumped through the A matrix
because it's literally where the
observation from the thermometer is
meeting the latent state beliefs about
temperature from the agent. But now at
the attention level one of those agents
could just turn that five into
a.5 by having 0.1 attention. another
agent um or another context for the same
agent could have a 10
attention. So then it's like 50 units of
surprise. So that's the difference
between the same five thermometer units
being for the purposes of basian
updating like it could be like a five a
five sigma update or a 50 sigma
update in terms of how surprising the
event was.
Andress.
Yes. Uh I'm thinking intuitively like
about a scientist with a hypothesis and
and this notion of confidence I and I
would also relate that to specificity
like um confidence can mean two
different things. Confidence can mean
like a moral state you know like are
you taking a stand or are you not? But I
think here first of all it doesn't mean
anything like that. It just simply means
given all the options
um how specific are you you know that it
is a certain way and not other ways. So
like when things are very
vague that's in certain sense that's not
having confidence in anything. It's just
saying you know or it's not specific.
But if you're a scientist with a very
specific hypothesis that that can be
inferred that well your confidence is in
that very high and your confidence in
everything else is very low. So when you
have a very clear specific hypothesis
you know quote unquote that you're
confident in then um you're really
subject to updating because there is
something to update. But if you don't
have anything specific, you don't really
have uh implicitly any notion of
confidence uh and there's nothing to
update u no matter what you discover
because you haven't taken any position
or any stand. So that would be I think
if if understanding confidence just
simply in this kind of default way then
the whole other notion would be well
what would it mean to have an extra
notion of confidence where you can
choose to be more invested or less
invested but then that would be a whole
separate question. I don't think that
that's the matter here, but that great
example, Andreas, and a great example.
So, it's like there's there's there's
two rooms. One of them has a uniform
distribution of temperature. One of them
has a hot spot. Now, there's two
investigators. One of them has a uniform
belief about the space. The other one
has this hotspot concept like they're
fitting a Gaussian or they're fitting a
DRock delta function to the room.
So it's like in the in the in the flat
temperature
room that sort of flat hypothesis
um is the right one and there's no
reason to pay
attention. But even paying attention or
not in that room would keep the keep it
the
same. Whereas in the uniform room, if
there's an investigator who is going to
really be paying attention to their
updating, then they're going to they
could be updating. They could just be
wildly moving that small Gaussian
around because they they had high
precision in in so at that level of
updating.
So it's just like that there's all these
all these kinds of examples help
separate out like there's like the
volatility of the environment, the
volatility of the updating, then there's
like the actual dynamics of the
environment and then the
um the relevance
um or the the accurate or veritical
nature of the agent's perception. Um or
this or this kind of question of like
does it learn other features like the
whole kind of Hoffman angle with just
the evolutionary game theory of of of
learning um cognitive structures that
you know surprise surprise are not the
exact structures in the world.
Yeah, those examples make perfect sense
now. Thank you. Thank you for the
explanations. it becomes very clear with
those examples and put that into
context.
Thank you. Yeah, it it
um there's a lot of statistical degrees
of
freedom even in a in a linear regression
type even just in the model itself, not
even getting into the kind of like
hypothesizing after results are known
like the HARK
um type like iterative inquiry or just
modifying aspects of the statistical
model, But just within like the
POMDP that um from from chapter 4 or
within a graph with not that many
variables like
this, it's
like first just the which which pieces
are on the board is already a
choice. Then there's all the connections
and then those connections can be
structured different way. And then those
connections could be kind of just taken
in their
plain first order
sense. But in a basian setting, if you
have just a plain first order variable
or matrix, it's like a
constant. So that might be fine, but
then it it is not necessarily learnable.
And even if it were a constant, there
still might be another more attentional
variable connected to it.
One benefit of of basian models in this
setting just yeah last point then MB is
in um
hierarchical parametric linear modeling
like explored in uh SPM you can only
test uh strongly models that are like
strictly nested with each other. So you
can test if you do the ANOVA just normal
scientific statistics like you have the
fMRI data and then you have their age
and their their weight and then you can
like test for you know factor A factor
AXB factor AXB XC
um you you can test those as nested
ANOVA and then you can say we found
evidence for an interaction between the
fMRI and age but we didn't find it for
weight. So that's that's the way you can
do the structural hypothesis testing
within
parametric classical stats. In basian
stats, you can use baze factor and other
just sort of empirical um methods to
just select models based upon their fit.
And they don't need to have a structural
relationship to each other.
Whereas in the linear
statistics, it's like it's more
constrained, but it's a more simple
test. And that's that's why there's just
so much similarity in in ANOVA
methods. And the SPM textbook has a lot
of this
information. Uh MB
Thanks. Yeah, I am just curious about
the model itself. So to use Andrew's
example, which I thought was great, I'm
a scientist and um I have a high degree
of confidence in my data, right? And
so I have a hypothesis and my h h h h h
h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h
h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h hypothesis
is confirmed by the data. And so I can
see how there's high precision, but
there that would be a to me that would
seem like a very low model update as far
as the the magnitude of the update. Is
that am I thinking about that in the
right way?
Yeah. Okay. So then I could also see
high precision ambiguous view. I'm sure
that it's ambiguous. Or you could have a
high precision low ambiguity view like
I'm sure it's this way.
Could I also I I could also see how I
would
have as far as the general model about
whatever that hidden state is. I could
say I have no idea what that hidden
state is, but whatever comes in this
channel here, I'm going to believe. So
that's that's like a probably a huge
belief update, right? Like I have no
idea what's coming. Whatever it is, I
see I'm I'm definitely buying it, right?
I believe it. Yeah. So I guess it
doesn't have to do with the you do slot
machine. You really don't know if you've
won, but the first observation that
comes in on on roulette, you're just
going to have 100% updating to whatever
it is.
Uhhuh. So, so I guess it's not really
about the certainty of the model itself.
It's the certainty of the data. And I
think that's the whole the whole point
of this, right? We have very precise
beliefs about how data are
generated then. So it's really not
necessarily about the the uncertainty of
the models. It's that second level
prediction. Is that right? I think
you're you're raising the sort of human
model interface of how much trust is in
that model or um or attention to that
model. But yet within the model what the
attention so not the not the human's
attention to this model's output. Mhm.
Just within the model it is it's it's
like a scaling coefficient
on on blurriness of input where you can
blur a channel to just basically be in
the backdrop of nothing or sharpen it to
to a high
layer. Am I jump? Yeah. Yeah. Go ahead.
Yeah. MB. Uh I think I disagree with
you. Um and the first thing is that I
think there's two completely different
notions of confidence at play here. One
that I think it's natural for us to be
injecting, you know, which would be like
human personal belief. I don't think
that that's implied here. I think all
they're saying is that when you have a
distribution, because they're talking
about any distribution, when you when as
soon as you have a distribution, if it's
peaked, you're implying that you have
confidence in that particular zone as
opposed to the other zones. If
it's flat, you
know, horizontal, then it just implies
confidence in any. I mean, you
know, just the shape of the distribution
indicates a certain type of implicit
confidence at play which has nothing to
do with mental states or you know like
our personal beliefs. It just it's
evidenced by the activity you know if
it's evidenced by the distribution. So
if you are
a sense and if you have just intuitively
to try to understand like like if you
have a clear hypothesis you can be
wrong. If you don't have a clear
hypothesis you could never be wrong. You
don't have a problem with being wrong.
If you if you're not going to be wrong
you don't need to be updated. If you can
be wrong you are at risk of being
updated. and you know so so I think
that's the that's the issue there is
that the more clear and specific you are
uh the more you will be open or
vulnerable to being updating yourself.
The more vague you are, the more kind of
like you frame what you say, the more
you just kind of make it all mean
nothing, the less that you have to worry
about updating.
Al although being very precise in your
beliefs but having no attention to to
input does not lead to updating either.
So it's not simply that having having
precise belief. That's why
there's these two notions of confidence
at play which I think has to be first
you know one is and so the idea of
attention see attention works with both
versions of confidence but I think the
version that they're talking about
attention is simply the fact that if you
focus on anything you know without
having any mental apparatus like a human
being but any kind of system that has
some kind of focus is going to as soon
as you focus you have a implicit notion
of confidence uh and If you aren't
focused, you have an
imp implicit of not really having
confidence.
So, and the implicit
implicit between the discrete world and
the continuous world, you know, like you
have these continuous
actions, they have a notion of
confidence, you know, like a specific
action, you know, that was taken uh
where there's no mental belief, but it's
a specific action. But also like in
modeling that with our generative models
or our like finite models like we have
also can have a notion of a specific um
thing or maybe maybe even a confidence
value. I don't know but I'm trying to
deconfuse. I don't know if I am.
Yeah, I I I hear you on that. I think
there's there's there's probably ways to
to write out and program all these
things. And again, there might be
situations where these models have the
same
um directional just they capture the
variance or or there could be some
contrived example or some pattern where
they capture different elements. But
it's like but again that that makes it
clear. There's the investigator with
precise or imprecise beliefs about the
room, about whatever their hypothesis is
actually about. And then they could be
paying attention to the thermometer or
not. And then that but that can look so
many different
ways just depending on what the state
spaces are because also like beliefs on
an information channel. It is a latent
state. Like if we have it's like we're
we're going around the room with a
thermometer and then there's some some
unobservable in the room which relates
to how variable the thermometer is.
That's like the
uh recurrent
switching linear dynamical
[Music]
system in the RX infer. It's like
there's a zero or one. There's two
underlying discrete dynamical
states. Two, just two states that just
are doing this
function and then they switch between a
low and a high variance mode. But you're
only getting these observations just as
the
um raw data
points. And then this could this could
um just as the variance estimator
changes you can infer that you're in a
different latent state. So these aren't
so different and partially it's because
people use latent state to sometimes
mean just environmental
states but when you get into the model
it's it you it gets more specified.
Sylvia.
Yeah, I just I thought of an example
just from a psychiatry computational
psychiatry point of view. If we think
about people with maladapted beliefs or
some sort of psychiatric condition that
made them have like negative beliefs
about the world and more often than not
their beliefs are very very precise. is
too precise even though it's inaccurate.
And the reason that they are not really
updating that belief is that they they
will actually purposefully ignore
certain data that would challenge that
negative model, the negative belief or
they will
selectively just choose the things that
will confirm that model and that's why
they they will appear to be trapped in
in that belief. I guess I guess that
would be an example um for the
differentiation that you mentioned about
on like whether you pay attention or not
um to to that data.
Yeah, there there could be a lot of ways
that in a in a complex model it plays
out, but like precision
on how how informative 0 to 100 beliefs
on the screen are taken to be and then
there's like the the epistemic foraging
of choosing where to
look. Whereas in a lot of these textbook
type examples, it's like the the agent
is just kind of locked into the one
stream of information and we're just
talking about the dynamics of one stream
of information coming in like the the
sequence of music
notes. But once you start getting into
like behavior switching or location
switching, that's that is whole
different spaces of what information to
choose.
But it's like everyone selectively
chooses
information and and some would probably
even extend that some that that all
selectively choose information to
confirm their model in the kind of
self-evidencing maximalist take.
um John and then address.
Um if you if you talk about the the uh
information coming in um you have to
somehow figure out the mutual
information between what what you're
seeing and what you want to know and
that in general is a very hard problem.
Uh so how would you how do you evaluate
that someone else has um you know uh
uh what's it called? Um psych uh I don't
want to say psychopathology because that
means something specific but uh
pathologies of the mind. Uh how how
would how can you tell from the outside
because you you have to you have to know
the in mutual information and that's
typically very very hard.
Yeah, short answer
um empirically the mutual information is
going you're going to call some computer
programming like package like mutual
information between these two
distributions. So there there's more to
um like what is the actual mutual
information or what is actually
happening but just at the sort of really
pragmatic
level mutual information is also going
to be conditioned upon what model you
have like if your if your model is just
a coin flip then you're only going to be
able to get one bit of information if
you are maximally imprecise about your
belief whereas like you know if you had
different beliefs about the coin flip
then you might get a amount of
information from it. But that shows just
quantitatively
um that the it the mutual information is
about the distributions in the
model. So then you can look and infer
different parameters in your model. You
fit your model to data and then you look
at the parameters of your model and
their variance profiles. Whether you do
it with classical like parametric
statistics or basian statistics or um
non-parametric like sampling based
methods you're going to get some graph
that looks like this. This could be like
the risk score of five different
properties. This could be that some
cognitive parameter for five different
entities or five different contexts.
So that could be wrong, but that is your
um calibrated and empirically driven
belief about a latent parameter
reflecting some cognitive phenotype of
interest that you explicitly specified,
right? But I I just don't see how you
get out of this situation of uh your
model's pathological. No, your model's
pathological. You don't have the mutual
information. No, you don't have the
mutual information. Oh, yeah. Yeah. I
mean, there's two Yeah. Okay. So now we
have two two um modelers meet and
they're they're drafting the DSM or
they're drafting whatever and then they
they um and then even on the same model
one could say well the threshold for
this or that should be 10% or it should
be two sigma it should be this. It's
like debating where's the threshold and
what to do with model
outputs for the same model. That's a
thing and then debating which
model that's there's that is another
space of discourse but just within a
given models's
output those yields beliefs on latent
state but what what you do with these
risk
estimates or what how you made and how
you selected your profile of risk
modeling
models That's That's not just like you
just make one and just take
it. Um Axel then Andreas.
I think Andreas was first so you can
Okay. Yeah, go ahead. I'll jump in. Um I
think um Sylvia's example relates to the
whole basil ganglial issue about uh how
can action be changed and I think that
belief changing may be very similar like
to changing the state of action and this
would relate to John's uh issues
regarding you know objectively talk
about
pathological thinking. So active
inference is very incomplete in many
ways. But with regard to this specific
type of issue, it's suggesting that if
you want to change action, you need to
lower your precision, you know, in terms
of your understanding of what the
current state is. Otherwise, you'll
never be able to get out of it. You'll
be stuck in a rut. And similarly like if
you want to change your beliefs, you
have to be able to let go of your
position and reduce it down so that then
you could re-evaluate and reclaim it or
to change it. And so if you don't do
these things, you'll never be able to
change your state of action. You'll
never be able to change your uh beliefs.
And it could be said like there's a
pathology in that in the framework of
active inference. And there's probably I
mean there's examples I think of where
you can see that neurologically but uh
it's it's just a general mechanism.
Yeah. But but there there are approaches
where people say the fact that I'd ever
update my beliefs is what makes me
right. And you know
uh trapped in the world of probability.
It's hard to
well there's a virtue to having very
strong beliefs. So let's say I believe
in God, but if I insist that the name of
God is, you know, uh, Joseph on
Thursdays and Mary on Fridays, you know,
like, well, am I willing to let go of
that belief and reclaim it? You see,
like not let go, but like to attenuate
it, you know, if if a person's not able
to attenuate it, that means that they're
not able to change beliefs. Then it's
not clear why to have beliefs, you know,
like why be alive in the first place. So
I think it's so it's just saying like if
you accept active inference as a
theoretical framework why um well but I
think the idea is they would have the
beliefs because they are there are
preferences that are adaptive right
there just a lot of pieces again it
doesn't necessarily need to apply to
this like self-standing of life a at all
this just can be understood and and
possibly more formally accurately just
at the level of variables in the
relationships, but there are some
intriguing parallels. But just I I don't
think every single analytical
relationship needs to um map to any
given psychological one when they're
simple motifs, but those are all
examples of things that deploy this
simple motif
in in intense
ways. Axel.
Yeah, thanks. Uh so I have a question
which is much less related to chapter 5
and also less related to these uh
philosophical discussions. So I don't
know if it's actually better to bring up
in another uh meeting if it's more like
practical implementation of active
inference. Uh but yeah I can ask if no
one else has Yeah, just go for it. Sure.
Maybe if I could share my screen would
that be possible? I can just show what
the problem is. Sure. Go for it. There
there is only but yes go for it. Yeah
sure.
I go fast. So basically uh I'm writing
my master's thesis right now and I'm
very interested in trying to combine
causal discovery with active inference.
So causal discovery is basically you
know you have uh different nodes. You
could have a causal graph that says X
causes Y which causes C and you're
trying to find out the true causal
structure. uh there's a lot of
literature on this but I thought it was
specifically interesting to use active
inference for this maybe specifically
for intervention selection. So for
example let's say you have all kind of
different variables and you have to
figure out how they um relate to each
other what causes what. Sometimes you'll
have to intervene on certain variables
in order to learn something. So kind of
with this example here, you uh wouldn't
actually from observational data be able
to distinguish between, you know, let's
say that X and Y and C are all
co-bearing, but you don't necessarily
know if it's uh Y that causes X and
causes C or this other one. So in order
to figure that out, you have to carry
out some interventions. And I'm kind of
trying to do that with active inference
right now. And I was hoping that maybe
uh some of this kind of
uh reducing uncertainty um and
minimizing free energy could be used to
maybe choose the interventions that were
the most uh um like reduce the
uncertainty the most and that would be
interesting. I've set up kind of a
simple example here where I have um a
true causal graph which is this one. And
uh here my states have become uh all the
possible uh values that these different
variables can take on. And I have some
um probabilities over actions. And I I
start out by just having my B matrix uh
complete. My A matrix basically uh is
known. It it says okay when the
observations are the same as states when
all these variables are 00 0 I will see
that they are 0 0 0 and then I have my
probabilities over actions where I am
able to do no operation so I'm not
intervening at all I can intervene on x
this is basically like toggling it so if
x was zero and then I intervene on x it
becomes one and so on and I run through
this example and I have my uh my um c
like I I start out my prior D. I start
out in this 0 0 state. My desired state
is to be in this uh second to last state
where X is one and Y is one and C is
zero. And then I kind of start out and I
run it. Uh and it says okay um you know
it starts out by having a equal
probability of all actions. I try X.
This takes me to the final state because
X causes Y to be one and causes C's to
be one.
Um and let's see here. Now I'm in this
final state and again I have equal
probability over reactions because I've
never been in this state before. And
maybe just to go a bit quicker over it
now because we don't have that much
time. What ends up happening is that I
keep getting into these different states
when I haven't been in a state before. I
haven't learned anything about where my
actions will take me in the B matrix. So
therefore I'll have even probability. It
takes pretty long time before I finally
get around to getting to the uh let's
see here the desired state which
[Music]
is have it here. So I get to the desired
state here
and now you'll see
that
because it's okay. Now this is of course
always with demos it doesn't work but
basically I end up getting to the
desired state that I want which is um
which is this state right before and
then I just keep doing no op. It takes
me a very very long time to get to this
place and I'm wondering if just quickly
and maybe anyone else also has some
ideas on this whether active inference
has been used for this kind of causal
discovery before and whether one could
learn the causal structure in less time
because right now it seems that my big
uh problem is that I I maybe learned
that no op doesn't change anything but I
only learn that in the first state and
then I have to also learn that it
doesn't change anything in the second
state and the third state and the fourth
state and so on And yeah, I was just
interested in any input on that and any
thoughts if anyone had some. Yeah, great
work. Definitely cool to see that kind
of direct active for the causal
discovery.
um when you are initiating these new um
slices.
Mhm. There are horistics that could um
accelerate and transfer the learning
like uh I if
uh if we have a room with all these
locations and then we have the heater in
the cooler, we don't need to learn that
the
heater we don't need to have a flat
prior on what the heater does at every
single square. So like instead of
initiating as a flat um belief when you
were bringing in these new blue ones,
they could just take the average of the
other ones.
Okay. But there's kind of no free lunch
because you could then you would be you
could there's a situation where that
will learn fast if the relationships are
transferable. But if they are then doing
not initi initializing the matrix with
like the rows or the column or whatever
averages or just or or however other
just initialization heristics can go
really far.
Would I be able to find this somewhere?
Has this already been this kind of
averaging or you just coming up with
this now?
Um I don't I don't know what specific
paper but I've seen it
in just regular
statistics and ways of doing
okay interesting and and then just maybe
one final question. So another way right
now the way that I'm setting it up is
that I'm uh
basically the states that I have are the
true combinations of all values that
there could be. Another way of framing
this is that instead of doing uh states
as the values, I actually do the hidden
states as the true causal structures. Um
so for example, I say one state is X
causes Y, the other is that X is caused
by Y. And maybe they're independent of
each other. are the three different
possibilities in this example. But if
you were to do this, then my hope would
be that you would finally learn the true
hidden state, right? Which would be the
true causal structure. H however, I'm a
little bit unsure about what would the
observations be for this, right? Um
especially because the observations in
the data would be the same for or at
least this and the first one and the
second one. That's like the simpler MDP
case. Like if you want to just do away
with the partially observable part and
the whole observation to latent state
mapping, it's like just working within
the latent space because observations
and the and the latent states are the
same. Sometimes people do that. Other
times um do still have the A matrix but
just make it an identity
matrix. So then you still get to use
observations and have a separator which
could later be fuzzed but you can start
with just passing it through basically
right and would the B matrix then be
useful at all because I'm thinking for
example here I mean the way that I would
learn like let's say um the way that I
would learn that X causes Y instead of
the Y causes X is that I would uh well
this is a very sick I would carry out an
intervention on the X. So I say like do
x set it to one and then maybe I would
see that if y changes when I change x
when I carry out this intervention then
I would guess that I'm in this state. If
y doesn't change when I change x then I
can infer that either I'm either they're
independent of each other or y causes x.
Um but then I feel like I would have to
create an a matrix for every single
intervention. Then I have to say okay if
I have uh if I try out an intervention
on X and I see that uh X and Y are
independent
uh then I know that I'm in one of these
two final states. If I see the Y
changes, I know I'm here. But that it
seems I'm getting a little bit too far
away from what active inference is. If
I'm creating like many many different A
matrices or what do you think? Well, one
one answer is it part it just depends on
whether you're continuing to do a
variational um or or expected or other
free energy. Like if you're still doing
policy inference with EF on the
B then these are just and then it's just
what question are you really trying to
ask like are you in a situation where
the causal structure is fixed and the
agent is inferring it or can there be
switching of the causal structure I mean
or or just what or can the agent act to
change the causal relationships or only
just kind of poke each of them to give
an output.
And that's kind of like the dynamic
causal modeling setting that again SPM
kind of led to which is taking in noisy
EEG fMRI data and then asking what is
the uh effective
connectivity in a structural dynamical
causal model of these brain regions like
is there any causal influence of the of
the uh implicit neural activity proxied
by the bold
on these two regions. If so, what is the
dynamical structural model for them? And
then they show in the textbook and like
this is kind of like why I come back to
it because it shows here's how it's done
with generalized linear modeling with
parametric classical stats. Approach
two, here's how it's done with basian
statistics. Here's here's pros and cons
of doing variational inference. Here's
here's pathologies and heristics for
priors. And then third way, here's how
it's done with non-parametric
statistics like bootstrap,
reample, which are like
non-parametric there. But so just the
the all those tools really well worked
for the brain imaging setting where
there's this like highdimensional noisy
lagged proxied fMRI measurement.
Mhm. But does it do you feel like it
intrinsically is there an intrinsic
motivation in the active inference
framework or drive to learn the causal
structure? Because in the examples I
showed you before, I was telling it that
I uh that my preferred observation was
to be in a certain state or have a
certain observation. In reality, I don't
have a preferred observation. I have my
preference is that I find the true
causal structure. Right? So it'd be very
hard to kind
of say that there's a certain
observation I want to see and that's why
I'm trying to maybe change the framing a
bit but I don't know maybe John he has
some yeah last comment but yeah I hope
you more and we can discuss it
more question for Axel actually. So
these X and Y are these propositions or
are these like states in a phase space?
Right now they're just states right now
they're binary. So x can be 01, y can be
01. Very simple. So the so so they're
boolean. So they're propositions, would
you say? Yeah, you could say that.
Well, it looks like y x implies y,
right? But it is kind of saying that x
is causing y. So if x is one, y will
also become one.
Yeah. And and there's there's just there
I'm gonna just end it just because it's
we're already past the time, but there's
a lot of a lot of cool work with causal
nets and petri nets and all these kinds
of things. So, thank you though for
sharing that. All right. Yeah. Thanks so
much for the input. Thank you all. Bye.